<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Bioinformatics | Dr. Tobias Baril</title>
    <link>https://tobybaril.github.io/tag/bioinformatics/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://tobybaril.github.io/tag/bioinformatics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Bioinformatics</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://tobybaril.github.io/media/icon_hua2ec155b4296a9c9791d015323e16eb5_11927_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Bioinformatics</title>
      <link>https://tobybaril.github.io/tag/bioinformatics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>MycoMobilome</title>
      <link>https://tobybaril.github.io/project/mycomobilome/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Oct 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tobybaril.github.io/project/mycomobilome/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Transposable elements (TEs) are found in nearly all eukaryotic genomes. Despite significant advances in the sequencing of genomes, TE resources remain sparse, leading to a lack of traceability, reproducibility, and duplication of effort when annotating TEs. Here, we focus on the fungal kingdom and present MycoMobilome, a non-redundant database of TE consensus sequences systematically curated using a set of 4,309 genomes covering all major clades. The initial database contains 276,641 consensus sequences after filtering to remove putative host genes and low-quality consensus sequences. We provide a consistent naming convention to surface information on the confidence in the classification including potential conflicting ORF functions, along with metadata to enable evaluation of TEs of interest and to determine whether further curation work is required on a case-by-case basis. Finally, we provide guidelines for community contributions, and encourage researchers to deposit new or curated sequences, which will be incorporated into future MycoMobilome releases.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Earl Grey</title>
      <link>https://tobybaril.github.io/project/earlgrey/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tobybaril.github.io/project/earlgrey/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Earl Grey is a fully-automated TE annotation pipeline designed to leverage the most widely-used tools for TE annotation. It aims to improve on current methods by automated extra TE curation steps in an attempt to generate maximum-length TE consensus sequences to aid in classification and annotation of TEs in a diverse range of genomes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Earl Grey Conda Package</title>
      <link>https://tobybaril.github.io/project/biocondaearl/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tobybaril.github.io/project/biocondaearl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Now Available in Bioconda!&lt;/strong&gt; Earl Grey is a fully-automated TE annotation pipeline designed to leverage the most widely-used tools for TE annotation. It aims to improve on current methods by automated extra TE curation steps in an attempt to generate maximum-length TE consensus sequences to aid in classification and annotation of TEs in a diverse range of genomes. Easy to install using conda package management.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Earl Grey Tutorial</title>
      <link>https://tobybaril.github.io/project/tutorialearl/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tobybaril.github.io/project/tutorialearl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Want to learn how to use Earl Grey? Take a look at this tutorial and learn exactly what Earl Grey is doing at every step, and also gain an insight into how to run Earl Grey on your own genome assemblies! Earl Grey is a fully-automated TE annotation pipeline designed to leverage the most widely-used tools for TE annotation. It aims to improve on current methods by automated extra TE curation steps in an attempt to generate maximum-length TE consensus sequences to aid in classification and annotation of TEs in a diverse range of genomes.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Docker Preconfigured Earl Grey</title>
      <link>https://tobybaril.github.io/project/dockerearl/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://tobybaril.github.io/project/dockerearl/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Earl Grey is a fully-automated TE annotation pipeline designed to leverage the most widely-used tools for TE annotation. It aims to improve on current methods by automated extra TE curation steps in an attempt to generate maximum-length TE consensus sequences to aid in classification and annotation of TEs in a diverse range of genomes. Here you can find a Docker image for Earl Grey preconfigured with Dfam 3.7 curated elements.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
